A Guide to the Dr. August E. Kehr Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-b
Dr. August E. Kehr Papers 1930-1986
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-b
ca. 2600 items
Dr. August E. Kehr
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library on July 17, 1986, by Dr. August E. Kehr of Hendersonville, North Carolina.
Biographical Sketch
See
World Who's Who in Science
, page 916, and
American Men and Women of Science
, (12 edition), page 3214.
Scope and Content
This collection contains ca. 2600 items (8 Hollinger boxes, 2.5 linear shelf feet), 1930-1986, chiefly the correspondence of Dr. August E. Kehr with nurserymen and other members of the American Rhododendron Society concerning the many facets of growing various species of azaleas and rhododendrons.
In addition to correspondence, the papers include articles, diagrams of the chromosome structure of azaleas, notes for speeches and talks, a journal of a 1977 trip to China containing notes on Chinese agriculture, newsletters, a brief history of the American Rhododendron Society, nursery price lists, photographs, a group of completed questionnaires on rhododendron breeding, and issues of the magazine
Rhododendron
, 1961-1970.
General topics of discussion in Dr. Kehr's correspondence include: exchanges of seed, pollen, cuttings and plants; registration of new hybrids, research on rhododendrons; publications; gardens; botanical expeditions; plant crosses; rhododendron subjects for talks at meetings; rhododendron controversies and disagreements; plant shipments; plant diseases; azaleas and other flowering plants; tissue culture; the merits of various rhododendrons, and magnolias.
Other particular items of note include: studies of rhododendron genetics(Bump, 1981 Jan 28; Green, 1981 Jan 21 & Feb 3); research & literature on rhododendrons(Binford 1980 Nov 24, 1983 Jan 28; McDonald 1983 Mar 18); handbooks and articles(Binford, 1983 Feb 7; McDonald 1984 May 8); The American Magnolia Society(Hickman 1980 Aug 26; Heineman 1980 Aug 11; Hopkins -many; Johnson -all; Melnick -most); a translation of a Chinese book on Chinese rhododendrons(Gambrill 1978 Nov 24, 1980 Mar 5; Young 1978-1980); Kenya n culture and agriculture prior to its independence from Great Britain(Cook -all); a reprint of the Royal Horticulture Society color chart (Egan 1983 Jul 1); Malesian Rhododendrons (Deul 1976 Sep 1 & 21); importing plants from England(Frisbie 1967 Aug 15, 1968 Apr 15, 1968 Oct 30, & 1968 Dec 29); Hardgrove hybrids (Hager 1975 Aug 18); Rhododendron Species Foundation(Hatheway 1980 Jan 23); and a Kehr genealogy (Purtak 1967 Oct 4 & Dec 11).
Organization
The collection has been arranged into two series, correspondence and topical files. The correspondence files are arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent, all of whom are listed separately in the guide; topical files are arranged alphabetically and chronologically within each folder.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence - A including: William L. Akerman, John H. Alexander, American Rhododendron Society Research Foundation, Carl R. Amasson, Edmond Amateis, Kenichi Arisumi, Elaine Averitt, and Esther Avery, 1962-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - B including: Bob Badger, Marge Baird, Sam Baldanga, Warren Baldsiefen, Dean E. Barber, Colonel [Paul?] Barber, Bob Barnett, John S. Basford, Jean Beaudry, D. Michael Benson, Warren E. Berg, Fred W. Bergman, Esther Berry, Benjamin Blackburn, Philip Blamey, Os Blumhardt, Bernis L. Bonney, Paul R. Bosley, Bob Bovee, Bruce Briggs, Dr. Edwin C. Brockenbrough, J. Judson Brooks, Maurice Brooks, Dorothy Brown, P. H. ("Jock") Brydon, Dr. Forrest E. Bump, Sidney V. Burns, and Dr. Max Eugene Byrkit, 1963-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Janet E. Binford, 1980-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - C including: Francis H. Cabot, Hugh A. Caldwell, Jr., Dr. H. Furman Cantrell, Ray Carter, Christine Casey, Carol R. Cerimele, Charles E. Merrill Trust, Arthur A. Childers, Bill Childers, J. Harold Clarke, Sir Ralph Clarke, Frederick W. Coe, Gerald E. Coe, Joseph H. Coleman, Jr., S. D. Coleman, Alleyne R. Cook, Ruth Cook, Douglas A. Cox, Peter Cox, Valleau C. Curtis, and W. J. Curtis, 1961-1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - William B. Cook, 1963-1964 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - D including: S. A. Dadlani, Ross B. Davis, Jr., Carl A. Deul, Charlie Dewey, Michael A. Dirr, Tom Dodd, Jr., Frank Doleshy, John Doppel, Robert P. Doss, Gerry C. Douglas, R. J. Downs, Peter Dummer, Henry Dumper, Edward B. Dunn, Ken Durio, and [Ged?] Dykrtia, 1966-1984 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Weldon E. Delp, 1981-1984 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - E including: S. Chris Early, [?] Edwards, James Egan, John E. Eichelser, Otto Eisenhut, John E. Elsley, Larry Englander, Dr. Arthur L. Ennis, Alva L. Erisman, Arthur T. Erwin, and Dr. John P. Evans, 1961-1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Edward and Fran Egan, 1979-1984 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - F including: Everett E. Farwell, Jr., Marge Farwell, Rudy D. Fecteau, Bill Fetterhoff, T. H. Findlay, Gerald Firak, Mary Fleming, Flick Family, Karl E. Flinck, Lewis Flint, Dr. David G. Fluharty, Harry Fowells, Ray Fowlers, Robert P. Fox, Marion Francisco, and Bob Furman, 1963-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Leonard F. Frisbie, 1961-1969 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - G including: Joseph B.& Caroline Gable, Frank B. Galyon, Kendall W. Gambrill, Rosie Gammons, Clifton Gann, R. D. Gantrell, James L. Gaupp, Bill Gensel, Juannie Gibbens, A. C. Gibson, Susi Gilbert, Russell Gilkey, Jeanie Gillis, Jerry Goodman, Jane Goodrich, Roger Gossler, Ana [Graeatt], Hugo O. Graumann, Kathy Green, Emma E. Greve, Gro/Tech Inc., and Molly Grothaus, 1961-1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Fred C. Galle, 1961-1981 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - H-I including: Velma Haag, Honore and Roy Hacanson, Betty Hager, E. Halas, Glanville Hall, Fred R. Hamilton, Ruth M. Hansen, William E. Hanson, Shirley B. Harry, William H. Hatheway, F. L. Haynes, Hank Hedges, John Heinze, Meta Heller, Leona& Rudolph Henny, Ethel M. Herbert, Dr. J. Heursel, Joseph W. Hickman, Philip H. Hickson, Andrew G. Hilen, Polly Hill, R. J. Hilton, H. J. Hohman, R. O. Holland, Mable Hollowell, Rhoda& Ira Holzman, Sir James N. Horlick, Geoffrey Houghland, Dick Houghton, Shiu Ying Hu, Bob Huber, Clay G. Huff, Regina Hughs, D. G. Huttleston, and C. Ingram, 1960-1986 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Harry Heineman, 1980-1986 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - W. D. Hogan, 1981-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Harry Hopkins, 1975-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - J-K including: Robert D. Jackson, Don Jenkins, Jenkins Arboretum, Richard T. Johnson, Adele Jones, Grady Jones, Henry Jones, A. G. Juknis, Mary Karr, Dr. Gary J. Keever, Bill Kehr, John R. Kehr, Wayne Kein, Don Kellam, Austin C. Kennell, Howard Kerrigan, Alden C. Kelly, Bruce G. Keyser, Don King, Edward King, Roy Klehm, Michael Klein, Anton M. Kofranek, Dr. Mark G. Konrad, Bob Korn, Howard Kuhn, Masaaki Kunishige, E. B. Kurtz, Jr., M. Kutschker, and W. H. Kvam, 1959-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Mary Lou Kehr, 1968-1980 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Lennarth Jonsson, 1983-1986 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - L including: George H. Lacy, Rose K. Lall, Bernice Lamb, Ben& Rose Lancaster, Dr. Henry Landis, Mitch Langbart, Dennis Ledvina, Chang Bok Lee, Betty M. Leishear, Dr. Tom Lelliott, [S.?] Lem, M. D. Levin, Lee A. Lichtenwalner, Bob Lindermann, Michael Lister, Anita Lockhart, Madeline Lotruglio, and Roger F. Luce, 1962-1986 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - David G. Leach, 1961-1985 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - M including: Thurston J. Mann, William J. Manning, Harold J. Marchant, Wallace Marley, Alex Martin, Howard W. Mason, Dick Matsuura, Marion and Vernon May, Marthaann Mayer, Dan E. Mayers, John J. McCabe, Joe McDaniel, Sandra McDonald, Jane McKay, Dianne E. McLeod, A. D. McNees, Gustav Mehlquist, Harry A. Menser, Louis Mensing, Dorothy& Raymond Miller, Ferris Miller, Julian C. Miller, William C. Miller III, Gary W. Moorman, Edward L. Morin, Frank D. Mossman, Bob Munger, and Mrs. J. C. Murphy, 1963-1986 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Alfred S. Martin, 1976-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - John May, 1968-1986 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Sandra McDonald, 1980-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Virginia Melnick, 1975-1986 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - George T. Miller, 1962-1975; (3 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - George T. Miller, 1976-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1965-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - N-O including: Perry Narten, Harry L. Nash, Jr., John Neal, G. G. Nearing, Ben F. Nelson, Ross Nelson, Erik T. Nilsen, Arthur H. Norris, Dan C. Opgenorth, Al O'Rear, Sr., Hadley Osborn, and Walter Ostrom, 1967-1984 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - P including: Edwin K. Parker, Ben Parry, Andy Paton, Harold Pellett, Melvin& Elizabeth Pellett, Dr. Carl H. Phetteplace, A. A. Pickard, Mary Adelaide Scott [Pierreport?], Radcliffe B. Pike, Lonnie M. Player, Gustav H. Poesch, Ward F. Porter, Basil C. Potter, Betty Powell, Orlando S. Pride, Martha Prince, and Otto [Pryl ?], 1961-1986 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Adolf and Eric Purtak, 1967-1968 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Q-R including: Mike Rachinsky, Herbert Racoff, Dr. G. S. Rai, Carol Ramsey, Paul E. Read, Dr. Reese, Louise Reich, Dr. Max L. Resnick, G. Reuthe, Olaf K. Ribeiro, Dr. Thomas L. Ring, Paul& Joyce Robinson, Dorothy W. Robinson, Mary Jane Rodgers, Dr. Tsuneshige Rokujo, R. De Roo, Royal Botanical Gardens, Royal Botanic Gardens, Royal Horticultural Society, Mary Ruegger, Ralph Rushing, and James Russell, 1960-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - George W. Ring, 1967-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - S including: Homer W. Salley, Dr. A. F. Serbin, Peter A. Schick, Dorothy Schlaikjer, Urban Schlitz, Lohna Schmidt, Brian Schram, L. R. Schreiber, Dr. Henry Roland Schroeder, Sr., Peter B. Schultz, Robert G. Shanklin, Francis Shield, Terry& Peter Sheuchenko, June Sinclair, Jim Skonieczny, Cecil C. Smith, W. David Smith, Molly Smith, Peter Smithers, Leon C. Snyder, Dr. Herbert A. Spady, Dr. Wolfgang Spethmann, Otto Spring, Ray& Esther Squires, Don Stanton, Dick Steele, Dr. Evelyn [Stevens?], Marshall G. Stilwell, Barbara Stone, Donald Stryker, Eleanor Stubbs, Pete Sulb, Maurice Sumner, Hideo Suzuki, Nancy Swell, Bernie Swenson, Dorothy Swift, and John Swisher, 1963-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - S(continued, see list above), 1963-1985 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - T-V including: Pat Tatum, Marie A. Taylor, A. J. Teese, Robert L. Ticknor, Bill Tietjen, Yu-Chen Ting, Jacob H. Tinga, K. R. Tobutt, Jim Todd, W. H. Tolstead, Charles E. Tubesing, University of Washington Arboretum, Ted Van Veen, and Bishop W. Von Wettberg, 1966-1986 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - Clarence Towe, 1978-1980 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - W including: L. K. Wade, Pat Walton, May& Cy Ward, Warid A. Warid, John Weagle, Dr. Franklin H. West, Ed Weston, Bob Whalley, Dr. Thomas Wheeldon, Frank B. White, Jr., Mark P. Widrlechner, John B. Wight, Jr., David G. Williams, Jack Wilson, Wanda A. Winner, Harry L. Wise, Bob Wister, John C. Wister, John A. Wott, Daniel C. Wright, Edmund Wright and Conrad J. Wrzesinski, 1961-1986 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - K. Wada, Hakoneya Nurseries in Japan, 1967-1969 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - X-Z including: Maletta Yates, John S. Yeates, Dr. Ernest H. Yelton, Judy Young, and Don& Edith Zaun, 1967-1986 (Box Box 5)
  - Greeting Cards, 1959-1985, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Professional Correspondence of Dr. August Kehr, 1949-1977 (Box Box 5)
- Series II: Topical Files
  - Articles by Dr. August Kehr, 1949-1983, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Articles by Dr. August Kehr and his Associates, 1951-1966 (Box Box 6)
  - Azalea Drawings and Labels, ca. 1980 (Box Box 6)
  - Information on Yellow Carolinianum, 1976-1977 (Box Box 6)
  - Journal of a trip to China, with notes re Chinese agriculture, 1977 (Box Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Materials, 1957-1983, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Printed, 1930-1979, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Newsletters and Conference Materials from various Rhododendron and Azalea Societies, 1966-1985 (Box Box 7)
  - Notes and Articles re the history of the American Rhododendron Society, ca. 1982 (Box Box 7)
  - Notes re a Speech Honoring Dr. Julian C. Miller by Dr. August Kehr, 1961 (Box Box 7)
  - Notes re a Talk on Rhododendron Breeding at Portland, Oregon, [ca. 1983?] (Box Box 7)
  - Notes re Talk in Seattle, "Putting Research to Work For You", 1983 (Box Box 7)
  - Nursery Price Lists, 1961-1985, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Photographs and Drawings, 1952-1980 (Box Box 8)
  - Questionnaire re Rhododendron Breeding, 1966 (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron, 1961-1970; (2 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - The Rhododendron Species Foundation, 1977-1984 (Box Box 8)